Guide to the Granville Stuart Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Granville Stuart papers
1864-1918
WA MSS S-1120
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.2
(1 box)
The papers consist of correspondence, writings, photographs, clippings and other papers relating to Granville and James Stuart and the early history of Montana. Much of the correspondence is dated 1916-1918 and consists of incoming letters and typewritten carbon copies of outgoing letters relating to information on Montana history, and Native American vocabularies. Principal correspondents include John E. Rees, Charles Kessler, William John McConnell, and Nelson Story. There are also short essays written by Granville Stuart and others on various episodes in Montana history, cabinet card photographs, of Granville Stuart and an Indian possibly identified as "Little Claw of a Grizzly Bear," and newspaper clippings on Henry Plummer and vigilantes. Other papers include a manuscript notice written by James Stuart calling for volunteers to join him in the Yellowstone, a manuscript appointment of James Stuart as captain of the expedition signed by ten men.
Stuart, Granville, 1834-1918
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Frederick W. Beinecke, 1971.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
GRANVILLE AND JAMES STUART
Granville Stuart, born in Virginia, settled in Montana Territory with his brother James in 1857. Granville Stuart was a member of the Territorial Council and in the Legislature, was president of the Board of Stock Commissioners, the Historical Society of Montana, and the Society of Montana Pioneers. He was commissioned by the State Legislature in 1916 to write a history of Montana.
James Stuart, Granville Stuart's brother, moved to Montana Territory in 1857. In 1864, James was elected captain of a Yellowstone expedition (his second to the area) to prospect gold on the Yellowstone River and to fight Crow Indians.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of correspondence, writings, photographs, clippings and other papers relating to Granville and James Stuart and the early history of Montana. Much of the correspondence is dated 1916-1918 and consists of incoming letters and typewritten carbon copies of outgoing letters relating to information on Montana history, and Native American vocabularies. Principal correspondents include John E. Rees, Charles Kessler, William John McConnell, and Nelson Story. There are also short essays written by Granville Stuart and others on various episodes in Montana history, cabinet card photographs, of Granville Stuart and an Indian possibly identified as "Little Claw of a Grizzly Bear," and newspaper clippings on Henry Plummer and vigilantes. Other papers include a manuscript notice written by James Stuart calling for volunteers to join him in the Yellowstone, a manuscript appointment of James Stuart as captain of the expedition signed by ten men.
The appendix contains an alphabetical listing of the correspondents.
Appendix A. Alphabetical Listing of Correspondents
- -Incoming
- - -Basler, E. R. ALS (see his "Pioneers of Pioneer" in Writings) -1917 Apr 17
- - -Bishop, Jean F. ALS -1917 Mar 10
- - -Garver, Frank Harmon. TLS -1917 Nov 23
- - -Hedges, Cornelius. TLS -1917 Nov 24
- - -Hickok, Lottie C., empty envelope addressed to -1889 Aug 2
- - -Hoffman, C. W. ALS -1918 May 6
- - -McConnell, William John
- - - -Typescript letter, carbon -1917 May 21
- - - -TLS (see his "The Mullan Wagon Road" in Writings) -1917 Jun 11
- - -McCulloh, Robert L. TLS -1916 Jul 26
- - -Quivey, Addison M., ALS -1880 Jul 8
- - -Rees, John E.
- - - -TLS - - -1917 Jun 3
- - - -TLS to Mrs. Stuart -1917 Jun 4
- - - -TLS to Mrs. Stuart -1918 Apr 8
- - - -TLS - - -1918 May 17
- - - -TLS to Mrs. Stuart -1918 Nov 8
- - -Steel, William Gladstone. TLS -1917 Apr 21
- - -Stuart, James (nephew of Granville). TLS -1917 Feb 7
- - -Stuart, Thomas. ALS -1879 Feb 11
- - -Vivian, T. J., ALS -1887 Apr 11
- - -Weaver, David B. TLS to Mrs. Stuart -1918 Nov 18
- -Outgoing (All typescript carbons)
- - -Basler, E. R. (see his "Pioneers of Pioneer" in Writings) -1917 May 7
- - -Friend, W. A. -1917 Dec 7
- - -Garver, Frank Harmon -1917 Nov 26
- - -Hedges, Cornelius, Jr. -1917 Nov 26
- - -Houstan, Mrs. E. L. -1918 Jan 8
- - -Kessler, Charles -1918 Sep 18
- - - - - - - -1918 Jan 3
- - - - - - - -1918 Jan 9
- - - - - - - -1918 Jan 14
- - -McConnell, William John -1917 Jun 15
- - -Rees, John E. -1917 May 25
- - - -Signed by Mrs. Granville Stuart -1917 Jun 1
- - - - - - - -1917 Jun 8
- - - - - - - -1917 Sep 18
- - - - - - - -1918 Apr 11
- - - - - - - -1918 Apr 22
- - - - - - - -1918 May 20
- - -Steel, William Gladstone -1917 Jun 16
- - -Story, Nelson -1918 May 20 -
- - - - - - - -1918 Jun 19
- - -Weaver, David B. Signed by Mrs. Stuart -1918 Jul 15
Copper mines and mining -- Montana; Crow Indians; Dakota Indians; Frontier and pioneer life -- Montana; Nez Percé Indians; Pioneers -- Montana; Salish Indians; Sihasapa Indians; Vigilance committees -- Montana; Bonneville Fort (Mont.); Fort Benton (Mont.); Fort Phil Kearny (Wyo.); Fort C.F. Smith (Mont.); Fort Union (N.D.); Idaho -- Politics and government; Missoula County (Mont.) -- History; Montana -- Gold discoveries; Montana -- History; Ophir (Utah); Salmon River (Mont.); Cabinet photographs; Photographic prints; Red Cloud, 1822-1909; Anderson, Reece, d. 1908; Basler, E. R.; Batchelder, George J., d. 1864; Clarke, Newman S., d.1860; Driscol, Dennis, fl. 1868-1913; Maginnis, Martin, 1841-1919; Marsh, Grant Prince, 1834-1916; McConnell, William John, 1839-1925; McCulloh, Robert L.; McDonald, Angus; Moise, Flathead chief; Mullan, John, 1830-1909; Plummer, Henry Amos, -1864; Rees, John E., 1868-1928; Reeves, Charlie; Richards, John; Steel, Will G.; Steptoe, Edward Jenner, 1815-1865; Story, Nelson, 1838-1926; Stuart, Granville, Mrs., d. 1887; Stuart, Granville, 1834-1918; Stuart, Isabel Allis Brown; Stuart, James, 1832-1873; Stuart, James; Stuart, Thomas, 1839-1915; Thompson, Edmund F.; Wright, George, 1803-1865; United States. Army. Artillery Regiment, 3rd; United States. Army. Infantry Regiment, 27th; United States. Army. Infantry Regiment, 9th (1855-1957); United States. War Department
- Box and Folder List
  - Correspondence
    - Correspondence, 1879-87 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 1916 Jul 26 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Scope and Contents
      Letter of Dec 7 to W. A. Friend includes excerpts of articles and despatches in the Montana Post, April-July 1865 about the "Massacres" at Ophir, typescript, carbon, and a reproduction of a sketch of the town
    - Correspondence, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Empty envelope addressed to Lottie C. Hickok c/o Mrs. Stuart, 1889 Aug 2 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Writings
    - Basler, E.R. "The Pioneers of Pioneer," typescript, carbon, corrected, [1917] (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Accompanied by an ALS from Basler dated 1917 Apr 17, and a typescript letter, carbon from Granville Stuart dated 1917 May 7
    - Driscol, Dennis. "Story of Corporal Dennis Driscol," holograph manuscript in Mrs. Granville Stuart's hand (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - McConnell, W[illiam]. J. "The Mullan Wagon Road," typescript, 1917 Jan 1 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Accompanied by a TLS from McConnell dated 1917 Jun 11
    - Reynolds, Joseph. "Indian Rock," manuscript (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Stuart, Granville. "Description of the Gun Owned by Henry Plummer," typescript, carbon, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Accompanied by holograph notes by Mrs. Granville Stuart
    - Stuart, Granville. "Discovery of Gold in Montana," typescript and typescript carbon. Incomplete: pp. 1-2, 17-19 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Photographs
    - [Granville Stuart], cabinet card photograph, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 12)
      Pencilled note on back reads "J. F. Ritchey, Garnet, Mont." Accompanied by a photographic plate of Stuart
    - [Little Claw of a Grizzly Bear?], cabinet card photograph, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 13)
      Sunbeam Studio, Helena, M.T.
    - Negative print of six scenes of [Virginia City, Montana?], n.d. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Clippings
    - Rheem, W. C. "Henry Plummer, The Notorious Road Agent of Montana", n.d.
      Related Archival Materials note
      See: Oversize, broadside folder 20
    - Rheem, W. C. "Moore and Reeves. A Brace of Early Day Desperadoes" Holiday Herald, [1882]
      See: Oversize, broadside folder 21
    - Unidentified. "The Butchery a Foregone Conclusion", [1876 Jul?] (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Unidentified. "Vigilantes of Montana", n.d.
      See: Oversize, broadside folder 22
  - Other Papers
    - Stuart, James. Manuscript notice, signed, concerning a trip to prospect on the Yellowstone River and make war on the Crows, [1864 Feb 15] (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Manuscript appointment of James Stuart as captain of expedition to prospect for gold and secure town sites, signed by 14 men, [1864?] (Box 1, Folder 17)
      Accompanied by a revised version
    - "Rules for Markers," manuscript signed by Granville Stuart, Capt. Deer Lodge Rifle Team and B. N. Tatem, Capt. Helena Rifle Team, [187-?]
      See: Oversize, broadside folder 23
    - Unidentified. Manuscript notes on remedies for stomach cramps, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - "E." Later manuscript note regarding a life sketch of "Stewart", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Oversize
    - Rheem, W. C. "Henry Plummer, The Notorious Road Agent of Montana," clipping, n.d. (Box bsd, folder 20)
    - Rheem, W. C. "Moore and Reeves. A Brace of Early Day Desperadoes" Holiday Herald clipping, [1882] (Box bsd, folder 21)
    - "Vigilantes of Montana," clipping, n.d. (Box bsd, folder 22)
    - "Rules for Markers," manuscript signed by Granville Stuart, Capt. Deer Lodge Rifle Team and B. N. Tatem, Capt. Helena Rifle Team, [187-?] (Box bsd, folder 23)